[Music]
uh
so
[Music]
hello everybody welcome to yet another
live episode of the ask a widget show
today is episode 61
and today is an episode in which i have
taken comments from the
questions from the comments and i'm
going to be answering those questions
questions that you all have asked in the
comments before i do that let's see who
all is there i can see migna roy
drishtiman om zaveri
you see big girl mega star
and many other people
great to see you all great to see you
all thank you so much for being here so
before i get into the comments
i would like to make one point i would
like to thank my friend rakesh
for pointing out that i habitually mix
up
ghazni and gore so ghazni and gore are
two separate geographical locations two
separate towns in gandhar afghanistan
and i think in in some videos i have
mixed these two up when i speak i tend
to mix these two locations up
so
so just please be aware of it and i also
kind of mix up the two terrorists ghazni
and gori so mahmoud of ghazni was a turk
who lived in the 10th and 11th centuries
and muhammad of gore
was an afghan who lived in the 12th and
13th centuries so i kind of
tend to mix up these two individuals as
well
gory ghaznavi gorgashni potato potato
tomato tomato you know
so
caveat m tour be aware of that and i
will try and remember that but i
probably will do that again in the
future
so just be aware of it
all right with that let's get into the
questions let us go into the questions
and uh well where shall we begin i think
we will begin where everybody with the
question everyone is asking
which is this
so this is a question by shubham but
it's i have got lots of different
variations of this question
i typically don't comment about the
breaking news and current events but in
this case i will do that
so the question is
so shubham says speak about this weak
government who gave up against
anti-nationals today
we expected good reforms etc
protests were bound to happen but they
gave up even though the majority is on
their side they betrayed us what is next
article 370 ca will also be repealed
and mr modi is the weakest prime
minister until date so that's the
sentiment that is being expressed here
and many people feel betrayed many
people feel upset that these farm laws
the three farm laws were repealed
yesterday
so the question is uh essentially
first of all why were the farm laws
repealed secondly
uh
is
mr modi a weak prime minister and
thirdly the question i'm getting is has
mr modi failed right so these are the
questions i am getting let me position
myself properly all right
so first of all the question is why were
the farm laws repealed well we don't
have i don't have sufficient data to
answer that question but it appears that
it is something to do
with national security
it looks like it was a national security
issue it was going uh the the situation
was going in a direction that would have
been
problematic for the country from a
national security perspective
right
uh
i mean lots of people are speculating
all kinds of things on social media
but i get the uh
feeling that there was something
related to national security which is
why
this step has been taken of repealing of
deciding to repeal the farm laws
so that is the center the the feeling
that i am getting national security of
course trumps everything else
and if there is a national security
issue then that information will not be
made available to the public
national security is a sensitive issue
and if certain developments are
happening
then those should not be shared with the
public
even though the government may look bad
so that is point number one that it
looks like there was something to do
with national security the farm laws
were enacted more than a year ago and
there were protests engineered protests
and all and eventually now they have
been repealed for certain reasons
uh
so is are all the other laws also going
to be repealed article 370 and ca no i
don't think so i don't think so
so this issue had been kind of
communalized and politicized the the
farm laws
and that's why it looks like it's been
repealed now the second question is
the second point that is being made is
that
mr modi is the weakest prime minister
until date based on what's happened
yesterday
okay i understand why certain people
feel this way and right now everybody
lots of people are saying that on social
media uh if you look at social media
twitter etc it's all abuzz with with
people taunting mr modi and saying he
has failed and he is the weak prime
minister and all that
including the certain uh channels that i
have been on in the past so they're all
saying that
and
i think if you are uh long-time viewers
of of uh of this channel
then you will be very well aware that i
have in the past been extremely harshly
critical of the government
in with respect to its policies about
education
with respect to its policies about
culture about rewriting history not
rewriting history not doing that
and also the kind of stagnation we are
seeing in this in the space
in the space race and many other other
things so i have been harshly critical
of this government now when it comes to
this thing
they rep the the decision to repeal the
farm laws
i am not going to be critical of the
government see consider two scenarios
consider two different prime ministers
prime minister a
uh makes a decision enacts some laws and
there are protests that are engineered
and they threaten the stability and
security of the country now this prime
minister prime minister a decides that i
am a strong prime minister no matter no
matter what happens
i will be firm and i will not take back
the laws no matter whatever happens even
if the country goes down in flames i
will not change my decision because i'm
a strong prime minister i will appear
weak if i do that so that is prime
minister a
prime minister b
says that let me see how things go and
based on the developments if the country
is getting destabilized then he says the
national security and the national
interest is more important than my
personal image i will apologize even
though i have done nothing wrong and i
will take back the laws this is called a
strategic retreat so which prime
minister do you prefer somebody who is
more concerned about his image
and he he will let the nation suffer for
his image
or a prime minister who is willing to
take the blame
and look
weak
but
as law he will do it as as long as the
national security and national interest
is not compromised which prime minister
would you prefer it's as simple as that
i would prefer i mean it takes a great
deal of courage and fortitude
to apologize even though you've done
nothing wrong and take back something
that you yourself enacted
and and you know how people are going to
react everybody is going to say what
happened to 56 inches
what happened to the strong prime
minister his
strong man image is broken blah blah
blah blah blah he is willing to take
that on his chest right
he has owned this he has owned the
taking back of the laws he says there
are certain politicians that when who
are such that when things go well when
they win an election they will take all
the credit
but they when they lose 10 15 20
elections they will say it is the fault
of the party
do you know who those politicians are i
think you know who those politicians are
in the case of mr modi
he has owned this
he has taken the blame on himself he's
not blaming his party he's not blaming
his ministers he's saying that it is my
decision to take back the farm laws
right
so that is called leadership
you may think he is weak or whatever but
you know
what is the the see it's not over until
it's over so the last question is that
it has mr modi failed right has mr modi
failed
so let me give us a slightly strange and
different example this year we have the
olympic games right
in hockey
india played germany in the bronze medal
match
and very quickly india went 1-0 down
then india was able to equalize it
became 1-1 and then germany slammed in
two goals and india was one three down
with less than half the match to go
so had india failed
when this these big setbacks happened
three one down three one is a terrible
uh
you know uh it is it is a very
precarious situation it's almost as good
as lost and less than half the match was
left so should india have decided that
oh we have lost we should give up no
india fought back
and even though india was one tree down
they eventually won five four
so the match has a certain duration
in in between
in the in during the course of the match
all kinds of things happen
there are ups and downs but you keep
fighting
so mr modi has been elected prime
minister for a five-year term right that
five-year terms ends in 2024
so i think the time to decide whether mr
modi has succeeded or failed
is in 2024
right now we are at the end of 2021
there is a long time to go
picture of ibaki friends
like they say
so i think what i would recommend is
that we should not react to everything
emotionally
life is full of ups and downs
it is all part and parcel of the game
so right now i agree there is a setback
mr modi wanted to enact the founders
they were beneficial for the for the
farmers for the small farmers it is the
karo pati farmers the millionaire and
billionaire farmers who have caused
created this the situation and it is not
only them who have done it there is an
entire international ecosystem behind
them who have done that the toolkit
ecosystem
it is in the face of these these issues
that mr modi has done a strategic
retreat this is called a strategic
retreat
it is a five-year military campaign in a
military campaign there are lots of
battles there is no no general in the
entire universe who has won every single
battle ching is khan lost his army lost
the battle of parwan
against the terrorist jalaluddin
kharagmi
but in the end ching is khan won so
changes khan won every single military
campaign but inside every military
campaign there are dozens of battles you
win some you lose some what is important
is that you win the military campaign
so there are long term objectives at
play
right
see india is on a path upwards slow but
steady it is not a three month game
it is a hundred year game it's a hundred
year marathon think of it like that ups
and downs keep keep coming so don't get
emotional
don't give up
keep your eyes on the long-term target
that's what i would say so i disagree
that mr modi is the weakest prime
minister until date i think he's one of
the strongest prime ministers until late
he shows what real leadership is you may
disagree with that this is my assessment
i am perfectly fine if you disagree with
that i i do i have nothing against that
my personal assessment is that mr modi
is a very good leader he is one of the
strongest prime minister we have had one
of the best leaders we have had this is
clearly a setback this is not what he
would have wanted
but there is a long way to go
the time to decide whether he has
succeeded or failed is in 2024.
until then let's wait and watch and
let's be positive shall we
all right
question number two
okay this is by utkarsh and karan two
separate questions but related questions
so utkarsh asks that in your opinion
what is the best way to uplift the
farmers of india and the other question
by current is that
how can we remove poverty from the
country from our country and these are
interrelated questions
see
in 2018 more than 50 percent of the
country was engaged in agricultural uh
in the agriculture sector sector and
associated sectors
and the total output the total
percentage of india's gdp contribution
of the sector was about 16 17 percent
so more than half the country is doing
this work but only 15 16 17 is the
contribution to the gdp
and i think as of today or the latest
figures that we have was that about 44
45 percent of the country is engaged in
agriculture and associated allied
sectors and the contribution to the gdp
is just like that you know 14 15 16 or
some something like that there abouts
give or take
so it is clear that the average farmer
is engaged in a very low income activity
it tells you that the average farmer is
a poor person
it is not something that is giving them
the quality of life that one would want
to have in a prosperous civilization
right
so it is clear that we need to uplift
these people from
well from either poverty or near poverty
so if we were to uplift the agricultural
the people
involved in the agriculture sector it
would bring a significant portion of the
country
the country's population out of poverty
or into uh into a better economic
uh situation so what is the best way to
do this
in my opinion
the best way to do this
is to take people out of agriculture
we don't need 45 of the population
involved in agriculture
this is the 21st century we have
machines
we have technology i think two percent
or three percent of the population of
the country should be involved in
agriculture
we can mechanize everything we can
automate everything this is the 21st
century so let two or three percent of
the population be involved in
agriculture let the private companies in
there should be obviously no
exploitation of everybody any of anybody
so most of the people need to be taken
out of agriculture
and they need to be set to work in other
sectors india needs to become a
manufacturing powerhouse
it is manufacturing
and industries that uplifts the nation
that skyrockets your gdp
germany is a manufacturing powerhouse
china is a manufacturing powerhouse
japan used to be a manufacturing
powerhouse the right way
to uplift the
population and to take a country
out of the low income domain into the
middle or high income domain is to
is to invest
large scale into into into
into manufacturing and industries
so all of these people who are
languishing
in very poor financial straits in the
agriculture sector they need to be
rescued from the agriculture sector
and their talents should be better
utilized elsewhere
that's what needs to happen
so that's why india needs to become
an industrial nation a nation that is
very much into manufacturing all kinds
of goods
right that's what needs to happen so in
my opinion that is the right way to
uplift the farmers of the country and to
remove poverty from the country and the
other thing that needs to happen for the
sake of the gods
is india needs to end corruption
the entire government governance system
the entire governance machinery not
entire but much of it much of it let's
say
it runs on corruption
what is corruption something that
happens outside of the laws
we all know that
everybody knows that
so corruption where is india's war on
corruption
and i'm not saying that the central
government has any corruption for the
first time in 70 i don't know how many
years we have a clean central government
for the first time in god knows how many
decades we have a
proper clean
central government but as you come down
the situation is different there is
corruption everywhere
and it especially
impacts the common man and woman at the
grassroots level so when uh is india
going to
declare war on corruption
so once that happens
a lot of the money that is being wasted
it is going into the pockets of people
who contribute nothing to the country
that money will actually be used
for the betterment of the country for
what it actually is meant to be used so
these are the things that need to happen
and if we do that if if the government
decides to do that
at some point in time
then we will be able to eradicate
poverty and become a middle income
nation eventually a high income nation
and the civilization we have always been
so these are the things that need to
happen
jyotish says please explain
civil society as a new frontier of war
fourth generation war and is india
losing this war
well
the farm laws were repealed
that is civil society as a frontier of
war what's been happening in delhi
in the the past two three winters
you had the shaheenbag riots
the shinebug thing or whatever then you
had the
the the former protests
do you know how much organization it
takes to organize a bunch of people and
organize protests you know how much
money it takes to to feed all these
people so that they can sit for months
and months on end all the coordination
that is required who is doing all this
do you even ask yourselves
there is some some
something behind this something at play
and this is what is meant by
the civil society as a new frontier of
war there are forces outside of india
from outside of india they are
controlling manipulating all these
things money is flowing in
unlimited money is flowing in
right all the coordination is being done
by various
uh
groups and organizations
that are exterior to india
they are mainly in the west some of them
are in other countries also
some of them are in canada some of them
are in the uk some of them are in north
america other places some of them are
being organized from pakistan and china
all of these forces are at work
trying to manipulate indian media
trying to
manipulate indian
uh perceptions and the mindset and
opinions via social media via the
mainstream media
and all these protests etc are being
organized they don't arise spontaneously
by the way
all these protests are organized they're
engineered so this is what is meant by
civil society as a frontier of war
is india losing to this war right now
right now it seems that india is not
able to do much to counter this
so that is something that needs to
change
i think it was mr ajit
spoken about this just a couple of days
before the farm laws were repealed
so all this politicize politicization of
the farm laws thing all the
communalization etc it is all
it is all coordinated
and it is all done from various other
locations or outside of india because
today the world is transparent there are
no real borders anymore
the world is one big village you can
talk instantaneously to somebody from
any part of the world at any time you
want
right and you can interact with them
at a moment's notice on social media etc
etc etc so everything can be coordinated
today worldwide globally
so that is the frontier the new frontier
of war
and today it is very easy to
influence the outcome of elections in
other countries
uh recently there was some african
country that banned facebook and twitter
because they were trying to influence
elections there
and the same thing is going to happen in
india in 2024 be ready for it
they are going to try and demoralize you
they're going to make you feel that what
whoever whichever politician you you
prefer
they're trying to manipulate your
opinions about that politician or that
party what whichever one it is i don't
care which it is
everybody has the right to their own
political opinions
you may be right or left or center or
whatever you may have certain political
parties that you prefer
or certain parties that you don't prefer
and it is very easy to manipulate your
opinions
based on the kind of trends that the
things that trend on social media the
kind of hashtags that train on social
media the kind of
influencers you watch on youtube etc and
so on and so forth so this is what is
meant by civil society as the new
frontier of war
you can actually engineer the mood of a
nation at a given at a given moment
using
trends and all that
so that is what india needs to
wake up to
or people say that india i mean india is
one of the best i.t sectors etc and all
but well you know india is still got a
lot of catching up to do when it comes
to this this is all propaganda this is
propaganda warfare information warfare
and so on so india needs to
uh
get its act together right now india is
not doing very well and you can see the
what happened just yesterday
so yeah good question
akash says all the citizens of china is
patriotic as indians are this question
arises from the news that many chinese
soldiers are drafted into the military
against their will
is there any hatred towards the
dictator-like rule of the chinese
communist party in common chinese people
what are the chances of a coup civilian
or military
a good question
so
so it's like this
i just spoke about uh
about uh the civil society as the
frontier of warfare in the case of china
they are a closed society they don't
allow google twitter facebook any of
this western social media giants they
have their own social media and that is
the reason why they are to a large
extent immune
to the regime to the regime change
attempt that the west keeps engineering
in places like india in india they try
and they try and manufacture opinion
they try and manipulate your your
perception of about things
and so on and so forth
in china that doesn't happen
in india we have an education system
that teaches you to hate your own
country and to be ashamed of your
culture
in china
the education teacher
education system teaches students to be
proud of being chinese and to worship
the chinese communist party
education is very very very powerful it
is a very powerful tool
children are very susceptible
to suggestion
and when you tell them something
repeatedly or year after year over and
over again it becomes
something that is part of their of their
psyche
and they can never get over that
so the chinese i would say are way more
patriotic than indians are
way more patriotic
today i would say that
how many indians are paid to attack
today
look at that fellow veer das
and lots of people have asked me about
him veerdas he goes abroad and maligns
india makes fun of india
and there are so many people who don't
have any
love for the country
people try tend to put their local
interests above the national interest my
language is more important my state is
more important than the country there is
so much sentiment like this
right
and there is so much sentiment about my
religion
is more important than the country
among certain sections of society
i mean you know
it is there it is it is a problem in
india i think india is a very fragmented
nation india doesn't have a sense of
unity
india doesn't have a sense of indian
identity
if you ask people what your what their
identity is they will say my identity is
so-and-so state my language or whatever
the hell there is
the indian identity always comes second
so we are not taught
to be patriotic
as children we don't know what
patriotism is we think patriotism is a
bad thing many people say patriotism is
is bad nationalism is bad
and they try to create semantic
differences between patriotism and
nationalism as if they even understand
the same semantics and linguistics but
yeah that's the thing
so i think there is
a great lack of patriotism in india
i mean i think that most of the people
who watch this channel are patriotic i
know that
but overall in the overall population
there is a significant
lack of this sentiment in the chinese
they are not programmed programmed by
the education system by the media by the
communist party um state machinery etc
to be extremely patriotic
and there is a contract a social
contract in china as long as the chinese
communist party is able to deliver high
standards of living
and
and victories for china globally
economic victories diplomatic victories
maybe in the future military victories
as long as that keeps going as long as
the chinese communist party keeps
succeeding people are going to support
it and they're going to stay patriotic
so i think the citizens of china are way
more patriotic than indians because they
have been programmed to do so
uh chinese soldiers are drafted against
their own will into the military yeah
that happens yes
so but that is a minimal thing i mean
the the chinese military is about how
what is the strength 2 million 3 million
something like that
approximately give or take
so that is the strength of the chinese
military the population is 1.4 billion
so that sentiment may be there um in a
small fraction maybe 50 percent of the
soldiers or maybe 25 percent of those
soldiers it is not a nationwide malaise
right
so i think that there is a
sentiment of devotion
and obedience to the to towards the
chinese communist party in the common
chinese people
the chances of a coup at this stage are
minimal the coup can never happen from
the civilian side it can happen
either as a political coup within the
chinese communist party or as a military
coup against the chinese communist party
there can be no civilian coup in china
the chinese as of
the chances of a coup right now are
minimal because the
chinese communist party so far is doing
well now the economy is slowing down etc
if that happens there could be internal
problems in the chinese communist party
people may try and overthrow mr xi
jinping and that sort of coup may be
engineered so that may happen if the
economic slowdown continues so that is a
possibility uh sometime in the future
uh surya desai says
should india change its capital because
delhi has become overpopulated extremely
polluted
also it's just a few hundred kilometers
away from the both the pakistani and
chinese borders
should we build a new city from scratch
or change the capital to one of the
existing cities
i think that's a very good question and
a good suggestion i think there's no
need for us to keep on using delhi as
the capital city
the capital city of a country should be
built only for administrative and
administrative purposes for governance
purposes it should ideally not be in in
in a highly populated
city or zone
it should be a purpose-built city
somewhere in the heart of india and the
only purpose should be to uh to house
the the parliament of india and the
administrative and governance missionary
of the central government
so and and delhi like you say it's
extremely overpopulated it's a very
polluted city and it is close to the the
chinese the tibetan border and the
pakistani border so it's a problem i
think delhi needs to be abandoned as the
capital and we need to build a new
capital city somewhere
in the center of india in the in the
central central region of india that is
a very good idea i think that should
happen but i don't know if there is
political will for that and delhi has
never been a city which has given india
good luck
i mean people people even say that delhi
is a cursed city from the time of indira
the indirect was delhi wasn't it
delhi is built on this side on the on
the location of ancient india
from the mahabharata times and from
there those days itself it has been a
city with bad luck it's been a cursed
city whoever has ruled there
has whichever indians have ruled there
have had bad luck i mean i don't know if
you believe in bad luck or not it's
luck is a different story but you know
it doesn't have a good history
so maybe india should find itself a new
capital city build itself a new capital
city
uh historically we have had multiple
capital cities uh during the kuchan
times during kanishka the great time we
had two capital cities one was mathura
and one was purushpur which is present
day peshawar
so maybe in the future we can use
peshawar as a capital city you know in
the future maybe five ten years on the
line
or maybe maybe longer but
as of now it would be good to have a
capital city
in somewhere in the central region of
india
equal distances from all the borders of
india that sort of thing
yeah that would be good i think it's a
good suggestion it's a good idea we
should do that
dungar singh johan says what are your
views on the metaverse
it's an interesting question so what is
the metaverse the metaverse is is is
something that's almost here already it
is the confluence the convergence of
three four different domains one is the
physical realm that we inhabit the
second one is augmented reality the
third one is uh is
virtual reality and then then you have
things like social media and
cryptocurrency and all that so
eventually all of these domains are
going to merge together into what people
are now calling the metaverse
so what may happen is that you may be
able to sitting in your room go and talk
to somebody
in another
continent as if you are in the same room
you can hang out with your friends you
may be in india somebody else may be in
europe third person maybe in africa
fourth maybe in north america maybe in
south america six may be in japan and
you can all hang out together in one
virtual room
as holograms as if you are all together
in the same room
that may happen soon enough maybe in the
next five to ten years that is the
metaverse
and you may have augmented reality like
your certain uh things that you wear on
your eyes goggles glasses that give you
extra information than what you're
already getting
and you may have elements of virtual
reality in that and then you may have an
entire cryptocurrency and virtual
payments domain and that so you may
actually inhabit
a universe
that is way more augmented and different
than the physical universe you live in
the physical universe may live may look
rather
threadbare once you enter the metaverse
so that that is the metaverse what are
my views it's going to happen we are
almost there
our lives are increasingly uh online
i mean is there a single day that you
spend without being online or without
interacting
with the internet and doing transactions
of some sort of of the other it's
impossible nowadays right
and it's only going to increase in the
future
so that is the metawars it's going to
happen whether people like it or not
and it's going to make some people very
rich
so the early adopters i mean right now
facebook has rebranded itself as meta
right
so
their plan is to take the take the lead
in creating the metaverse and being at
the heart of the metaverse
and other big companies from the us
mainly are also doing this
so it remains to be seen what uh
what role india plays in this i will
india be a passive consumer
or will india be
to some extent a creator of this
so that's what it is right
so that is what the metaverse is
okay
says hello from pakistan hello hello
nice to meet you
what have you what are your views on the
theory of hellmund or harot river in
afghanistan being the rig vedic
saraswati
and general jd bakshi in many tv shows
has said the length of the saraswati
river was four thousand six hundred
kilometers
in the rig vedic period but if we now
see the maximum length from mount
kailash to
kutch is about two to two and a half
thousand kilometers that's a very good
question
uh okay so yeah there have been many
theories about the helmund
or some other river in afghanistan being
the rig within saraswati there is even a
harahavati river in somewhere in iran
that people have proposed could be the
saraswati
right
so the helmund ini hellman originally
was called the setu mantra river the
original name was
then later it became
hitumanth because the parsis the
persians they
river means a river with a dam on it
so that was the original ancient
vedic sanskrit name of this river so
apparently our ancestors many thousand
years ago had built a dam
on this river
so this river this is
the helmand is about one thousand one
thousand five hundred kilometers long
give or take it's not a very long river
and it is a river that dies in
afghanistan itself it it drains into a
lake in afghanistan let me share my map
let's go to the map
it's always a good idea to share a map
and take a look let me see where is our
map
here we have a map
so let's go to afghanistan north of
india gandhar
and where is the helmand river so this
large big
big river here is most likely the
hillman let's see what it's called
helmand
this is the helmand river as you can see
it's a fairly long large river it goes
from northern afghanistan
all the way to this region here there is
this big lake here that it drains into
and that is the end of the hillman river
so this is where the helmand river
ends more or less
somewhere in this region
right okay so the hellmann river
ends somewhere here it never reaches the
sea and there is no dry riverbed of this
river that that indicates that in the
past at some time at some point in time
in the past it may have actually drained
into the sea that is not the case
so this river does not ever drain into
the sea and it did not do that in the
past also and it is also not a very long
level river it's about a thousand two
thousand five hundred kilometers long
and it is known that the saraswati is a
river a great it was a great massive
humongous super large
river that drained into the ocean
so that's why the helmond will not fit
the bill and neither will any other
river in afghanistan because none of
these rivers they actually drain into
the sea
and we also we know that there is only
one massive dry riverbed in the entire
saptasindo region from gandhar to up
only one massive dry riverbed which
stretches from the himalayas
and goes all the way into the
into the indian ocean in kacha
so that is a massive gigantic dry river
bed it is several kilometers wide in
some places so that is the only
river
that could possibly fit the bill of the
of of the
that could possibly match the
description that is given in the rig
veda of the saraswati
it was called the mother of floods a
loudly roaring river it was a mega mega
river it was bigger than any other river
in this region bigger than the sindhu
river so that is why i
would not take the claim
of the hill month being the saraswati
seriously because it simply doesn't
agree with the data that we have right
or the river the hara
is an even smaller smaller river it's a
minor river compared to the helmand so
these two rivers do not fit the bill you
know that's the thing now as to what
general
uh gd bhaktisir has said in tv shows so
i am not aware of what he says what he
has said uh if he has claimed that it
was so and so
kilometers in length i am not aware of
it i am not privy to such uh i have not
heard any such claim or maybe he did
maybe he did not i'm not sure so since i
have not heard it myself i will not
comment about that
now
what is the length that is mentioned in
the rig veda so the rig weather i'm not
sure how it has been described the
length of the river but the units that
were used in the vedic times were most
likely yojanas right i think it was
yojanas and we are not quite sure of the
conversion from the rigvedic or ancient
vedic units to kilometers
because we have lost the data we've lost
the information that would enable us to
accurately convert from that unit to the
modern kilometer unit and therefore it
is i would i would be very careful
to pass any judgment as to what length
is given in the rig veda or any ancient
way the text of this river
right
so that's why i i'm not sure what is the
exact length that was mentioned if if an
even
if a proper in entire length is given or
not even in the rig weather
but
from all the information that we have
the geological information the satellite
data
and the on the the ground information
the information we have on the ground
level of this enormous
riverbed enormous riverbed that we have
in front of us
which stretches all the way from the
himalayas to the
to the indian ocean so there's only one
such
dry river bed that we have available to
us so from all this information that we
have all the data that we have
it we can only
we can only conclude that that has to be
the location of the saraswati and we
know that this dry riverbed i mean
they've conducted tests and all that on
this river it is uh
estimated that this river
dried out
approximately around 1900 to 1500 bce
which is about three and a half to four
thousand years before today so that kind
of matches
uh the
what uh timelines one would expect right
so from all this information one can
only conclude that that only can be the
saraswati and not the helmand or
the iranian
which seems to be a name given by the
vedic people who
migrated to iran and they named another
river in the in memory of the great
river that they had left behind it looks
like there is a case so there is a
iranian harahavati river a small one
which seems to be named after the great
and original saraswati river
so
that's what i have to say based on all
the information that we have
the best candidate for the
vedic saraswati is the great dry
riverbed
that stretches from the himalayas all
the way into the to the indian ocean in
kutcha that is 99.9 percent the correct
river the correct candidate for the
saraswati
okay avinash kali says
why are there no purple
or green stars this is a very good
question
has your teacher
ever
made you think about this why are there
no purple or green stars it's a very
good question
so uh
let me
let me answer this question it's a very
good question i like it and let me
answer it so here is
okay let's take a look at this so let me
ask you a different question first of
all to answer this question why are
there no purple or green stars
see when you take a piece of metal let's
say a piece of iron and you heat that
piece of iron
what is the transformation that you see
you first see as you start heating the
piece of iron that the p that the piece
of iron the iron rod
starts glowing the initial color is a
dull red color
then as you heat it further as the
temperature rises it becomes a bright
red color then it becomes orange
and yellow
then it becomes bluish white and that is
the final color before it melts
you never see a piece of iron
glow
green
or purple
even though it emits those wavelengths
of light if you can see here so if you
can see my mouse pointer this is the
black body spectrum which is the rainbow
which is the rainbow right
and the the uh metal that you heat it
actually emits light in all of these
wavelengths it emits initially red light
then orange light then yellow light then
it emits green light then blue and
purple lights as well
and yet you never see it that way
why is that
it's not because it doesn't emit that
light of that color it's because we see
the human eye
sees the light differently
so even with stars there are stars that
emit light in all these colors
for example our star the sun
it's it like it's light
peaks in the in the green
uh in the green part of the spectrum and
yet we don't see it as green we don't
see any green light coming from the sun
it's because of the biological uh
construction of our eyes our eyes uh
have two kinds of photoreceptor cells
rods and cones one of these cells it it
it detects the kind of the amount of
light that comes in the luminosity and
the other kind of cell detects colors
so human eyes
the i'm not sure exactly what the
biology is
but we are unable
to see the the
green light that is detected because it
is kind of drowned out in all the other
uh colors of the spectrum that are
emitted so when it becomes greenish we
kind of see it as white
and similarly we don't see indigo or or
purple we see that
it all blends together and looks like
white light so if you see the light of
the sun it is white light the sun looks
yellowish to us
but the light that comes comes out of
the sun is white light it is a
combination of all the colors of the
spectrum put together
and our our eyes do detect
red they do detect orange and yellow and
they do detect
uh blue to some extent but they somehow
interpret green
and the purple end of the region of the
spectrum as something that's mixed
together with all the other colors and
that's why it all looks white to us so
it's a biological thing
it's a biological thing it's not a
physical thing
so
there are stars that emit light of all
colors there may be stars that emit more
green light too or purple light too and
yet we don't see it that way we see them
most likely as white stars so when you
look in the sky you will see stars
twinkling in various colors
many of them look blue some of them look
white some of them look yellowish
oranges some of them look red but we
never observe stars that look green or
purple so that's the reason it's a
biological thing our eyes are designed
in a certain manner that they do not
perceive that sort of light coming from
stars they see it only as white
but the light does the green light does
come out of stars the same weather green
light is emitted by heated metals but we
don't see it our eyes don't perceive it
it's a perception issue not an emission
issue
alright so i hope that answers the
question
stars emit light in all colors but we
don't see
it that way
okay akash says why doesn't india de
recognize tibet as part of china when
arunachal pradesh is not considered a
part of india by the chinese
who recognized it in the first place and
why was it nehru
let me answer the second part of the
question first who recognized tibet as
part of china
it wasn't sharing who did that
it was shri atal bihari vajpayee
who officially
recognized tibet as part of china in
exchange for china
recognizing sikkim as part of india
sikkim
tibet
so in exchange for china recognizing
this tiny sikkim is part of india
mr vajpayee
decided to recognize officially the
whole of tibet is part of china
incredible so this was another gandhian
move actually
so that that is the the story of india
people
our leaders giving i mean making such
unequal
arrangements and treaties
so the question then is why doesn't
india d recognize tibet as part of china
when the chinese don't recognize
arunachal pradesh as part of india they
say it is their territory and they don't
believe in the one india policy but they
want us to uh follow a one china policy
so here's the thing
let's say tomorrow india de-recognizes
debate as part of china india says tibet
is a disputed territory
what is going to be the chinese reaction
it's not going to be anger
they are going to take certain steps
see today
china is the world's manufacturing
powerhouse
it manufactures all kinds of
spare parts ingredients things that you
need in your supply chains and all that
right
and there are lots of things that india
needs from china
lots of goods materials
spare parts things like that our
industries need spare parts that are
manufactured in china we need
semiconductors we need other things that
are manufactured in china the chinese
will stop all the supplies
it's essentially economic sanctions and
trade sanctions
so when we stop receiving these things
such things from china our economy will
suffer a significant setback
so china is currently today in a
position to impose a great amount of
pain and cost economic cost on india
by simply shutting off the tap
and refusing to give in to send india or
any of these supplies
and that is the leverage they have over
india so this is the chinese started
uh developing their manufacturing sector
back in the 1970s the late 1970s early
1980s and they have slowly steadily
invested in that and made it more and
more uh
and and
seen a great amount of progress so
initially they were they were
manufacturing just very basic things but
as the expertise grew they started
manufacturing more and more complicated
instruments and and things and today the
entire global supply chain
is fed by chinese manufacturing
right and they are able to manufacture
anything in the world
so they can shut that down for india or
any other country that does not uh
recognize tibet or taiwan etc as part of
china that they can impose genuine costs
on on such a country especially india
so that is the reason there are real
reasons why india is not
taking such an action
and india had the opportunity to do this
before china
but india never did that even today
india is not really
well it has not progressed much in
the field of
in the manufacturing and in other
sectors right so
india will have to
build its economy grow its economy to at
least
10 trillion dollars
in gdp before india can think of
challenging china in in such a manner
so there are real
genuine economic
and geopolitical reasons why india is
currently
not taking such an action
aditya says what is meant by
electromagnetism so there are four
fundamental interactions in nature four
fundamental forces you can say
the strong nuclear force
that holds
atomic nuclei together
the weak nuclear force
that is responsible for radioactivity
etc
then you have the electromagnetic force
and then you have the force of
gravitation these are four the four
fundamental interactions
electromagnetism
is one of these
so what does electromagnetism do
electromagnetism is what makes like
charges repel and unlike charges attract
it is what it is the
uh so electricity and magnetism are two
different manifestations of the same
force they're part and parcel of the
same force and the mediator particle the
boson
that is involved in electromagnetism is
the photon
so light is an electromagnetic
phenomenon and
the
and electromagnetism is the force that
holds
atoms together
so
in an atom let's say you take a hydrogen
atom which has one proton in in is the
nucleus and one electron
which goes around it
so the proton is positively charged the
nucleus is positively charged and the
electron is negatively charged so it is
the electromagnetic force that holds the
atom together whether it is the hydrogen
atom the helium atom or oxygen calcium
iron uranium etc you can go on and on so
all atoms
in every atom
the electrons
and the nucleus are are they stay
together because of the force of
electromagnetism
and then you have uh
all the chemical uh
chemical
chemistry when you talk about chemistry
when atoms come together to form
molecules that is also because of
electromagnetism and intramolecular
force forces are also because of
electromagnetism the the whole of
chemistry is based on
electromagnetism so the world we live in
it is mainly
an electromagnetic world our sensor our
senses
are based on electromagnetism
the light that we see is an
electromagnetic phenomenon so all of
these things are
uh
manifestations
of electromagnetism
okay chi-ching says
who were the ancestors of the people of
present-day nagaland what is their
origin and were they part of ancient
india this is a very good question and
this is a question that we don't have an
answer to as of today historians don't
know what is the origin of the people of
nagaland so let's talk about the people
of nagaland where is nagaland do you
guys know where it is
most people don't know
where nagaland is let me once again go
to the map
where is the map
okay we were in northwestern india let's
go to northeastern india or the far far
east of india so this here region
this year if you can see the my mouse
pointer is nagaland
it is a state in the far east of india
to the south you have manipur to the
north you have assam
to the east you have meghalaya to the
west you have myanmar or burma so this
is the state of nagaland who are the
naga people the naga people are a number
of
of of tribes okay so there are a number
of tribes in nagaland you have the
konyaktar tribe the aotra the lotha
tribe wrong
mao sumi etc a number of tribes so
historically these tribes were
all living in this region and many of
these tribes were living in isolation
this is a very hilly region okay by the
way it's a very hilly region that's very
easy to stay isolated if you're a small
tribal community so many of these tribes
may have been isolated for a very long
time
many of them speak very different
languages they can't understand each
other's languages and they all practiced
so now they're all christians but
a hundred years ago even 60 70 years ago
many the majority of them practiced
their ancient uh
indigenous culture mainly animism nature
worship ancestor worship that sort of
thing
and many of them could not
understand each other's language so you
had tribes that were living in isolation
many of their tribes are very big
and many of them many of these tribal
groups are currently found in
present-day
manipur
some of them are found in arunachal
pradesh many of them are found in parts
of myanmar as well so these this is a
a large number of
different tribes
so when the british came to india
they categorized all these people as
naga as nagas so it is an exon it's a
name that's been given
by outside forces
now the the
so what is the origin is the question
right so we know that when the homes
came into
when the homes migrated to assam into
assam in the 13th century
these uh naga tribes what are now called
naga tribes they were already present in
in this region
they were already there
when it comes to uh
the money see the the major kings that
ruled this region were the manipuri
kings the mata kings the ning thoja
dynasty which goes back at least two
thousand years most likely three and a
half thousand years
now in manipur there is this saying that
the people of the hills and the people
of the valley are brothers the people of
the valley are the metes of manipur and
the people of the hills are the various
tribes the so-called naga tribes
so if the manipuris if the metis are
three and a half thousand years old if
that that's their history
then it is possible even the nagas may
have been living in this region for
three and a half thousand years we
simply don't know our historians have
not done their duty they have simply
neglected the northeast in the case of
manipur they have their own records of
kings they have their own historical
records and that's why we know the
history of manipur when it comes to the
nagas nothing there is no history i
don't know if history was written or not
but we don't have it today
but
i would think that it is quite likely
that the people of nagaland the various
naga tribes may have lived in this
region for two three thousand years or
even longer we don't know some people
say some some historic some historians
say that nagas came from china or nagas
came from
from
[Music]
mongolia etc i mean where is the
evidence
people
these days make claims without evidence
i think it is quite likely quite
possible that they may have been living
in this part of india in this part of
the world for a very long time it is
quite possible it's quite likely what
needs to be done is that the
historians need to take some interest in
this region and find out what is the
origin one of the ways to do this is to
do genetic analysis genetic tests of the
of the populations
if you do genetic sequencing of these
genomes of the the people of this region
manipuri's nagas people of arunachal
pradesh et cetera we'll be able to find
out what are the migration patterns and
when these migrations happen how many
centuries ago how many thousands of
years ago
as of today it's not been done and
secondly i'm sure that the various naga
communities various naga tribal groups
etc they have their own mythological
histories their own foundational
histories and all stories and all that
if you go and talk to the village elders
and all they will have their own
histories of their community so why has
this not been documented what are the
so-called professors in the university
of nagaland in the history department
doing
they are not doing anything
i don't know what they do
so it is
unfortunate
that we don't know as of today
the
origin
and the history
of the people of nagaland they are a
very diverse people very interesting uh
culture very beautiful culture their
ancestral culture
yeah
so
it would be i i would be fascinated to
know i would be very interested to know
what is the the deep history of the
people of nagaland what is the deep
migration history if there is any or
have they always been living here for
many thousands of years we don't know
but this is the kind of research that
needs to happen india is a gold mine
when it comes to historical research
when it comes to sociological research
when it comes to genetic research and so
many other things unfortunately our
intellectuals
our historians
our academicians our eminent
people they simply don't care
sad isn't it
okay karthik says what is your opinion
on school college dropout culture in
india can we get jobs only based on
skills without having a college degree
today it's not possible because our
industrialists and people who run all
these companies private sector etc and
the government sector actually
etc
they are enamored with degrees if you
don't have a certain degree they will
not even think about giving you a job
now contrast that compare that
with somebody like elon musk
elon musk has a number of companies
spacex and tesla are two of the
major companies
he has made it very clear that he is
open to
accepting anybody
in tesla as an employee provided they
have the right skills
and degrees are not important even if
you don't have a college degree he said
even if you don't have a high school
degree he will take you
as long as you can pass the coding test
and you can pass the interviews it's not
about degrees anymore
it's about
your skills
so in places like tesla places like the
us when you have a visionary
founder like elon musk
then it's possible
to get a job without a college degree or
even a high school degree as long as you
have the skills as long as you have
demonstrable skills
right
as of today indian mindset is very
different our
the people who run indian private
companies most of them are old men
and their mindset is still mired in the
1960s and 1970s unfortunately
if i were running a
company i would say i don't care about a
degree show me your skills if you have
the skills if you can demonstrate your
skills i would be happy to give you a
job but i don't run a company as of
today right
and oh so today being so today i would
say that dropping out is not a very good
idea in the us
if you look at people like bill gates
if you look at
the founder of oracle
if you look at steve jobs the founder of
apple
if you look at elon musk elon musk the
founder of spacex tesla
uh he was involved in paypal solarcity
the boring company and so on so forth
these people are dropouts
bill gates was a dropout steve jobs
dropped out of college because he found
it a waste of time elon musk was
accepted for a phd in stanford in
physics
he could have had a phd in physics and
written
you know published papers but he dropped
out after two or three days because he
he realized it's not the right place for
him
if you are doing a phd you have to
please
your professors and their academic staff
and whoever is there they all
hold your life at their mercy
so this is not the kind of uh
the the kind of environment that that a
a performer likes you know
having i mean
other people controlling your your
future and your destiny so i think that
dropout culture is still
not a thing in india now here is the
thing
in the next five to ten years maximum
this is my prediction
in the next five to ten years hear me
out
automation and ai
is going to get rid of all the useless
jobs in the world including in india
right it's going to get rid of all the
of all the low-level jobs
people like a ticket ticket checker
or if you stand in or or somebody who is
a ticket dispenser
in a station in a railway station etc
everything is going to become automated
by soft with software everything is
going to go online all these jobs are
simply going to be eliminated today the
indian bureaucracy etc and all that is
like a employment generation skills
scheme
very soon in the next five to ten years
all these jobs are going to disappear
and the only
the only thing of value
is going to be
proficiency
in high technology
you are going to be valuable in the job
job market only if you are extremely
super comfortable with high technology
if you are able to learn and adapt
quickly
and there is no degree for that
so i am telling you in the next five to
ten years degrees are going to be
worthless even in india
and those
industries those companies that insist
on degrees they're going to be left
behind
they're going to be left far behind and
newer more agile startups and companies
are going to come up which will not care
about your degree which will only look
at your portfolio and what you can
demonstrate
about your skills
and about how fast you can learn how
fast you can adapt so in the next five
or ten years it's going to be it's going
to happen and people won't care if you
have dropped out of college or school or
school even
because today there are
there are kids who are
into coding
into gaming and all that i mean you
might think that gaming is a waste of
time but it gives you certain skills
that are very useful and valuable
especially if you combine that with
coding and programming and all those
abilities
so in the future very soon
your proficiency and your skills
when it comes to high technology are
going to be the most valuable thing and
that's when dropout culture will become
the norm because degrees are even today
i think it's a complete waste of time
the education system is unfortunately at
waste of 15 20 years of people's lives
it gives you no real skills
it turns you into brainwashed mentally
damaged sheep
right
it it reads it it
it prevents you it it kind of
takes away your ability
to reason critical reasoning critical
thinking
asking questions creativity all those
things so it's going to change very soon
so it's it's not a thing yet but it's
going to be a very big thing in the next
five to ten years
okay my friend soham chaudhary says
what is the history of hinduism in
armenia
in the internet there is a wikipedia
page for hinduism in armenia
so if hinduism
exists existed in ancient armenia
then why is there no evidence of
buddhism in armenia even though armenia
is geographically closer to central asia
which is a buddhist majority region
okay if there is
okay central asia is not a buddhist
majority region
okay let's go to the map
let's go back to the map
this is the map where is central asia
uzbekistan
turkmenistan azerbaijan all this is
central asia all right
this is a muslim majority region it is
not about this majority region
in the past it was a hindu buddhist
region before the the turkification etc
of this region yes i agree
uh two three thousand years ago you had
the sketchians who lived across this
region it was called skithya the skits
the sithians were an
indian origin people
historians called them iranian people
but they were in indian origin people
and so on and so forth but today it is a
muslim majority region in the past it
was a hindu buddhist region hinduism
buddhism same thing it's not a different
thing i will tell you a hundred times
so in the past this was a hindu buddhist
region you had indian origin people
living or in this entire region people
who migrated out of india and these
migrations are very well documented in
indian literature
the
lingua franca of this region was the
gandhari language about 1500 or 2000
years ago or maybe even a thousand years
ago right
and this entire region all the way up to
present day western china the xinjiang
region
all of this
was
a region where you had a very
significant indian influence
and you will still find ruined stupas
and temples in this region so yes there
was hinduism and buddhism which is the
same thing in this region and the same
goes for armenia where is armenia let's
find armenia
armenia is a small country right here
it is
north
west of of iran
so this is iran here and you have
armenia there it is
east of turkey it is east of anatolia
and is essentially in the caucasus
region
which is kind of the dividing line the
imaginary dividing region between asia
and europe
now the armenians
are a very ancient people
and there was a significant presence of
hinduism in armenia there were many
hindu temples here you will not find
references to that on wikipedia i
suppose i've not seen it
but there were many hindu temples here
the many dynasties that were originally
indian in nature
and many there were temples
of lord ganesh of shiva etc these
temples were destroyed and christian
monasteries were built on top of those
and later recently even some of those
christian monasteries were destroyed so
there is a very old
there was a long time ago about 2000
years ago
significant presence of hinduism in
armenia if you look at the people of
armenia they don't look like europeans
uh they would not be categorized as as
so-called white people right european
people they their appearance is
different their skin is
somewhat darker than european the skin
of european people they would look like
the
typical person in let's say northern
india so or something like that the skin
color
and they don't they don't typically have
blonde hair they have dark hair and
brown eyes so their facial features and
physical characteristics are more
eastern than western and by eastern i
mean they look more like indian if you
see a person from armenia you would get
the feeling there is something going on
here there is some kind of connection
with india
but this is not all very well documented
historians of course don't want to
document the hindu history of of a
foreign country so we don't know much
about it i mean
by that i mean it's not very well
documented but there was a significant
presence
of indian culture of indian genetics of
hinduism buddhism in central asia and in
armenia
gargi says
you always keep on saying that indians
have great minds but how come we have
the worst education system in india and
we still manage to get to have great
minds out of the system
yes i will keep saying this that indians
are the most intelligent people in the
world and history bears this out
ours is the oldest and greatest
civilization today we are not the
greatest civilization we are not even a
civilization anymore
but we still
retain the same genetics we are the
descendants of the same great people
why do we have the worst education
system in this country in india
because we were colonized
because in the past 1000 years what
happened was that our indigenous
education system was destroyed
first by the turks and what was left of
it was destroyed by the british
and then they imposed their foreign
macaulay in education system on india
which is designed to
mass produce
clerks
and peons not leaders
not intellectuals not scientists not
artists it is designed
to mass produce clerks and peons
and there is a mindset that all students
have today
obedience
so today so so that is the reason why we
have the worst education system in the
world in india the the
see what this education system tells you
is
don't think
believe
don't understand
don't question
obey
believing blindly blindly memorizing and
blindly obeying is going to turn people
into sheep
even if you are the most intelligent
person in the world it's all it's all
about the wrong beliefs
the wrong attitude and the wrong values
that are being brain
that are being drilled into the minds of
indian children
right
so that is the there was the purpose of
the education system to destroy the
country to destroy the civilization to
turn india into a nation of clerks and
peons and followers and sheep
not a nation of leaders
right
and of course we still manage
to extract some great minds out of the
system
it's just luck
we have greatness in our genes we have
greatness in our blood in our minds
most of us are are beaten down by the
system and broken by the system by the
education system but some of us
we we come out of it and we climb oh we
climb above it
so somehow we still manage to have great
mind that come out of the system
especially when you have a population of
1.3 billion you will statistically have
a few great minds coming out of the
country but if we change the system
we will have millions of leaders coming
out of the country who will lead india
lead the world in a variety of fields
in technology in science in the arts in
politics in other in other things in
space travel in many other things right
in culture
so we need to have a society that
produces leaders in a variety of
different fields and domains today we
don't have it because of the education
system if we change it if we get rid of
the system and bring in a good education
system then the whole country will be
transformed
says how do i as an indian work for the
maximum development of india
good question i'm assuming you're a
youngster i would say this
to work for the maximum development of
india
you should spend the first 20 years of
your adult life
working for the maximum development
of you
the first 20 years
focus on yourself
it is not selfishness
it is personal development
so the first 20 years of your adult life
work on your personal development
maximum development once you reach the
age of 40 give or take
then contribute to the country because
then you will have reached a position
in which you have a great number of
skills you have a great amount of
experience
and you may have reached a position
where you can financially make things
happen
right
that's when you can work for the maximum
development of india because by then you
will understand how the world works
you will understand what are the
problems we'll know what are the
possible potential solutions so that is
what you do it's a long-term game it's
not something you can start at the age
of 20. it's very hard to do that because
at the age of 20 you are clueless i was
clueless at the age of 20. it doesn't
work like that so it takes time 10 20
years to gain experience to gain the
skills to become financially
self-sufficient to become financially
successful and powerful and that is when
you're in a position
to contribute to the development of
india that's what india needs
anjali says what if somebody doesn't
want to leave bharat in that scenario
how do we beat the ills of our system
and work up the ladder in our respective
profession like budding researchers etc
well anjali
i would suggest that the only scenario
in which you should not leave india as a
youngster is if you have a lot of money
if you have a lot of money
you can build your own startup if you
have good ideas or you can invest in a
startup which has good ideas
right if you have money you can make
things happen
but if you are starting at the bottom of
the ladder corporate ladder or the
academic ladder then the system is going
to prevent you
from flowering
let's say you're a budding researcher
you want to let's say do research in
physics
have you heard of any significant
research breakthrough coming out of
india in the field of physics in the
past 20 years
past 30 years
past 50 years
nothing right why is it so
because the system rewards mediocrity
and destroys talent
the system doesn't want
good people
the system is a system of mediocrity the
higher you rise in the system the more
mediocre you are
the talent they require is talent in
politics
so
the people who rise to higher positions
in academia arise because they are good
at playing politics not because they are
good
in research
heads of department etc are are
administrators they're not scientists
but they are the ones who are called
eminent scientists
so i would give you this honest
uh recommendation that
that if you don't wish to leave bharath
then you should be somebody who is rich
who has a few crew rupees to throw
around either to start a new startup or
to invest in a good startup otherwise i
would recommend that you should
leave india
for the first 20 years of your adult
life
establish yourself
in whatever field
you are interested in
acquire a certain stature
and then you can come back to india and
contribute to the country
that's what i would recommend
because today india doesn't want
talented people
and it is not the fault of the people of
india it is the system that is built
like this and unfortunately people
conflate the system with the people
because the system is so rotten the
indian people must be so rotten it's not
the case the system is the colonial
system that has been imposed upon us by
force
so anyway that's what i would say in
delhi
good luck
okay two questions very similar
why do indonesians have sanskrit names
when the cholas were based in the south
of india
and sandra prakash says with due respect
and curiosity
i'd like to ask you
on what basis do you say that the cholas
spread sanskrit in their kingdom in
southeast asia
very good questions right good questions
let's take the first question first
yes indonesians are sanskrit names and
the cholas rule indonesia
but the chulas were based in the south
of india they were a southern indian
dynasty they were a tamil dynasty
so why do indonesians of sanskrit names
very strange isn't it
my question is this
why do tamil people have sanskrit names
there is this uh very famous
individual periyar
periyar is not his name what is his real
name
his real name was ramaswamy
is that a tamil name or a sanskrit name
think of any major tamil
politician
actor or whatever whoever is your
favorite person
the chances are that they have sanskrit
names the majority of the names
of the tamil people
are sanskrit names
think about the old tamil movies you
used to watch
on doordarshan or whatever what kind of
lifestyle that tamil people have
they were devout hindus
there were more traditional and more
devout hindus than the people of north
india then what happened the past 20 30
years
that's all politics
and unfortunately today's tamil people
youngsters especially they think that
the the tamil civilization is separate
from indian civilization there was a
secular civilization hinduism is foreign
to tamil nadu and so on and so forth
utter
nonsense
so the indonesians have sanskrit names
because the cholas spread their culture
and civilization across southeast asia
and that culture that civilization was
hinduism and
sanskrit
okay that's why it happened
because the cholas themselves
had sanskrit names
rajaraj
raj raj what is raj
it is rajya
sanskrit
rajendra chula what is rajendra again
come on wake up
what about mr sandhya prakash or yeah
on what basis do i say that the cholas
spread sanskrit in the kingdom in the
kingdoms in southeast asia in their
empire in southeast asia see
we know there was sanskrit throughout
southeast asia
that is an undeniable fact we know there
was hinduism across southeast asia up to
the philippines throughout southeast
asia again an undeniable faith a fact
we also know
that it was the cholas
who conquered the whole of southeast
asia that is also an undeniable fact
there was no other indian empire that
conquered southeast asia two plus two
equal to four
the cholas conquered southeast asia and
there is sanskrit and hinduism across
southeast asia so who else would have
spread it
who else would have spread it
that is the basis on which i make this
claim
it is called logic
okay ardhan says
how and why did india lose the 1962 war
against china
well
how did we lose this war
so it all began in the 1950s
in the 1950s what happened was that the
chinese
they conquered they invaded tibet right
tibet was until then a sovereign
and independent
nation about this nation a dharmic
nation the chinese under mouth
invaded tibet
and they would not have succeeded in the
invasion because tibet is an enormous
territory
it's a it's a huge territory let me show
you
see this entire region here if you can
see my mouse pointer this entire region
here essentially is tibet it's a very
large
territory
so the chinese in the 1950s i think in
55 was it yeah
they invaded tibbett and they
started starving they were so far away
from actual china
and the supplies were were disrupted etc
and they were starved the chinese
soldiers were starving the people's
liberation army soldiers were starving
and their invasion of tibet was going to
fail
and what happened
is that our
magnanimous and magnificent prime
minister shri jawaharlal nehru
supplied them with rice
so that they could complete their
invasion
of tibet
so the tibet invasion succeeded
because our prime minister shri neheruji
supplied the people's liberation army
soldiers with
rice lots and lots of rice from assam
etc
that's point number one so the chinese
then
for the first time in
three to four thousand years of history
became actual neighbors of india until
that time there was no india india china
border it was just that india tipped
border but then the chinese invaded an
occupied tibet they annexed it and made
it part of their country and then the
india tibet border became the india
china border the india tibet border was
never properly defined
because india wasn't under the british
raj and the british was an illegitimate
foreign occupier of india
now in the 1950s again what happened was
that the chinese started constructing a
road
in aksai chin which is a part of india
they started constructing a road after
in annexing tibet
and for years mr nehru was unaware about
this when he came to know about this he
said it doesn't matter there is not even
a blade of grass grows there so let them
have it
this huge piece of indian territory let
them let the chinese have it
so that's point number two
first
the chinese would never been have been
intimate mr nehru brought them there
secondly he gave up on accident without
firing a single bullet thirdly mr nehru
neglected the indian army
the indian army did not have proper
supplies they did not have proper
ammunition they did not even have proper
winter clothing alpine clothing which
you need to the warm clothing that you
need to wear when you fight in the
himalayas where the temperatures can go
to minus 20 minus 30 degrees right
the indian soldiers did not have proper
equipment and proper clothing
suitable for that sort of climate
and they did not have ammunition etc so
the the morale was down
and and so on and so forth these are
many of the reasons why india eventually
lost the 1960 war
and also when the 1962 war happened mr
nehru for some reason
refused to allow the indian uh air force
to strike at the chinese positions
he refused the to allow the indian air
force to participate in the war so the
indian soldiers were fighting the
chinese without any air support
why would he do such a thing
i i don't have any answers for that so
these are some of the reasons why india
lost the 1962
war
against china
it is all thanks to the great
the great shri nehru
ashna says what's your viewpoint about
italy's one euro homes
so in case you guys are not aware italy
has been putting up certain
houses
for sale
for the price of
one euro
there are many websites
on which you can actually find these
properties
you can buy such a property for one euro
you want to do that do it now
but here's the thing
these are not
new properties these are typically very
old buildings buildings that are several
centuries to 300 years old
in
rural parts of italy very beautiful
locations and all that it is a beautiful
place right
but typically these are very old
properties in rural parts of italy so
italy has been for facing this
population decline for a very long time
for many decades
many villages are like half abandoned
today
and many of these buildings ancient
habitations have been abandoned many of
them are just barely standing heaps of
stones you could say
so the deal is that you have to buy this
one euro property for one euro only and
then you have i think about three to
five years something like that
in which you have to renovate the
property and the renovation is gonna
cost you money
maybe 10 000 euros if you're lucky maybe
50 000 euros maybe one lakh euros
it's gonna cost you money
and what you find is that the majority
of these properties are being bought by
foreigners not by italians because
italians know
that it may not quite be worth the
hassle
right so these properties are available
for sale if you want to buy a property
for one euro you can actually buy it if
you know where to look but then there is
a whole uh
there is a whole other thing a bunch of
other things that comes with that you
you have
i think three years or five years to
renovate the property and there is all
the paperwork to be done the bureaucracy
in italy is quite bad
there's a lot of red red tape and all
that so in the long run if it is
something that you enjoy renovating an
old property then you may be able to do
it if you have the money for that
otherwise it may not be worth your time
but yeah it's there the the scheme is
still i think open
uh the first
it was first started like maybe 10 20
years or maybe even before that ago
and it is still available so yeah it is
there but you may end up with a bad
property that is beyond repair
or you may
end up having to spend a lot of money on
it
it's not something that you can just go
and live in it's going to be something
you will need to renovate but many of
the locations are good with a nice view
of the countryside or even the sea
the climate is good in italy and so on
so it's it may be worth some people's
time
akar says
how soon will a time come when fighter
pilots are replaced by heavy-duty drones
and artificial intelligence and what
about the total replacement of human
soldiers by robotic soldiers in the army
and on ships in the navy
very good question it's going to happen
so in china let's say let's talk about
china for instance in china they have
these mig-19 planes in india we have the
mig-21s the the mig-19 is i think the
one of the world's first supersonic jet
fighters
it's a soviet design the chinese
acquired some of these planes and then
they created their own version of the of
the mig-19 i think it's called the y16 i
don't know what it's called y6 y16
something like that
it's a chinese version of the mig-19
plane
so these planes are very old museum
pieces but they have
brought these back into service as
flying drones
as unmanned aerial vehicles so these are
throwaway pieces that anyway belong in
the museum if they crashed it doesn't
really matter so they have converted
them into flying drones unmanned aerial
vehicles
so they will be remote controlled and
flown as fighter jets or maybe as
kamikaze aircraft they'll caught flying
bombs or whatever so that is what the
chinese are doing the americans have
converted some old aircraft
and even some f-16s into
unmanned vehicles
heavy duty drones you could say it's
happening
soon enough you will have drones that
are completely autonomous
completely ar ai powered that is also
going to happen
uh that is going to happen maybe it's
already happening we don't know
so it's it's already it's all of this is
already in the works
uh the chinese have a very very uh
extensive
drone program they have been investing
in
in drone technology for at least 15 20
years
and they have a whole lot of varieties
of drones that they have they have
created over over the years and tested
and they keep on improving
because they have this research-based
university program they have
universities that are only research
based many of them you know
so they have an academic industrial
military
research complex which we lack in india
because our academic academic system is
the 19th century colonial system which
doesn't care about the future of the
country
so the chinese are going ahead in this
the americans are also doing the same
but india thus far is not
a major player
when it comes to drones
we do have the rustam or something
unmanned aerial vehicle which is a
remote controlled aircraft which is
showing a good progress
but we have a long way to go to catch up
with the cutting edge level technology
so the time will be soon maybe in the
next 5 10 maximum 15 20 years when
fighter pilots are completely replaced
with
ai
in
in fighter jets
and the total replacement of human
soldiers by robotic soldiers in the army
and ships it may happen
uh i think we are still not quite close
to that because
we still don't have the technology
uh
for bipedal robots i mean there are
certain uh companies in the u.s that
have these videos of this dancing robots
dancing humanoid robots dancing dog
robots and so on and so forth so they
are
doing significant progress in that but i
am not sure if we are still
close to the to the point where these
these robots could serve or could
replace human soldiers maybe it could
happen in the next 10 years perhaps
so you could have these
robotic dogs and robotic humanoids
equipped with automatic weapons and
other things it could happen in the next
10 years
and also you may have the same sort of
thing in the navy in naval forces so
it's certainly going to happen at some
point
it could happen in the next five to ten
years
roughly
sushma says how is russia able to
develop a world-class military hardware
despite its low and shrinking economy
and why india lacks in this despite
having a good economy while
why do we lack research and development
what's keeping us behind
see russia the russia of today is the
successor's successor state of the ussr
the ussr was a genuine economic and
military superpower they had a massive
economy and
that translated that economic might
translate it into military might so
they invested in rnd
over the decades 1950s 60s 70s 80s 90s
and so on so forth right
so they invested a lot in rnd a lot of
their economy a lot of the money was
poured into r d and that's why
that's why present day russia has
inherited
all those technological advancements
and that techn and that rnd
and
industrial infrastructure
so they did not have to create all this
from scratch
that's why they are able to develop
world-class military hardware despite
having a small and shrinking economy
because they have the benefit of all the
iterations of submarine designs that
have been
created since the 1950s
and the various fighter jet designs that
the sukhoi and the mikoyan grove
and other design factories
have uh
produced over the decades and so on and
so forth
they they were one of the first powers
to develop uh
rockets so their rockets their initial
rockets were based on german designs
and then they iteratively progressed
upon that improved upon that and that's
why they have very good rockets today
they have some of the most powerful
rockets in the world
they are developing even more powerful
rockets so it's because they inherited
all the work that was done
during the soviet union that's why
they're able to do this
and india
did not invest in rnd did not invest in
its own
uh
military infrastructure
and all that
until very recently
so we just kept on buying
arms weapons etc and
military systems hardware
from other countries from the ussr and
later from the west
because
because politicians somehow
benefited from that
and that's why they did not allow indian
scientists to develop home-grown
versions
of these weapons
so until recently we were buying
howitzers cannons etcetera from beaufort
from sweden
we are still buying aircraft fighter
aircraft from other countries
we are now slowly
uh
creating the infrastructure and the
capabilities
to make our own weapons but it is going
to take time so that is what's keeping
us behind and also we don't have a
research oriented academic system
our eminent scientists and professors
they don't do any real research
have you heard of any genuine research
significant research being done in india
in the past 30 40 50 years nothing
we do have drdo we do have hindustan
hal
these organizations but they are simply
creating
hardware
and
weapon systems
that are imitations of what has already
been created in the west
in the u.s in russia in europe in china
we are simply trying to catch up we are
not creating something that is cutting
edge
first of its kind we are not doing that
so that is the problem we there is no
innovation there is no culture of
innovation in the govern in the
government in the bureaucracy because
all of these institutes institutions are
run by bureaucrats
and the bureaucratic mind
is not your ordinary indian mind it is a
colonized mind so these are some of the
problems that are key that are keeping
india behind
how to change the post-colonial
inferiority complex of the people of
bharat
for example when we say that these
things were present in our ancient
scriptures in science or
in our ancient civilization people don't
believe it but if we say that certain
western scientists historians doctors
anybody
proved it then people immediately start
believing it
why do we people of parath always need a
western reference to believe our own
things
here is the thing again i would i will
give the same example
if an indian scientist comes up with a
discovery or some some new thing
it indians will be very skeptical
but when a western researcher points
something out
then indians readily believe it why is
that
it's very simple
have you heard of any indian scientist
or any indian scientific institution
coming up with a major discovery or
major breakthrough
in science in physics
in technology in chemistry in
biochemistry biology molecular biology
anything any field in physics in science
has any scientist in india or any
institute in india come up with us with
any
new discovery or breakthrough in the
past 50 years or 70 years world-class
breakthrough
nothing
because there is no real research
happening in india and that's why
indians don't believe indian scientists
but when somebody from the west point
something out indians believe it because
the west has been achieving things
they have been
building breakthrough after breakthrough
in technology look at the technology
that we have today it's all western
technologies it's all been developed in
the west
right
computing
telecommunications indians did not
develop it we are simply consuming it we
are consumers
our scientists are not leaders
our scientists are not researchers
that's the real problem
and it is not because our scientists are
not good enough it's because they're not
allowed
to do anything
india's academic system
it unfortunately
prioritizes mediocrity over our
brilliance
it identifies
talent and destroys it and it promotes
mediocrity
you will see that in
the iits
you will see it in other institutes
you will see mediocre professors who
rise to the top
mediocre researchers who don't who don't
do any real research
no real research
so that's why indians don't believe
it when some indian scientist says
something but when something somebody
from abroad says it indians believe it
so what is the way around this we have
to reform the system
we have to create a system that rewards
talent and destroys mediocrity
it punishes mediocrity and revolves
talent
then you will see all kinds of
innovations discoveries inventions and
breakthroughs coming out of india
and that's when indians will start
believing in themselves it's as simple
as that
reforms india needs reforms
when will the reforms happen we need
reforms in the education system we need
reforms in the academic system
we need
research oriented universities not
teaching oriented universities
and so on and so forth
so i have spoken about these things
extensively in previous episodes you can
check it out
okay shubham says why is it hard to
develop a model that can predict
earthquakes
because we don't have sufficient data
see the earthquake earthquakes are
something that happen inside the earth's
crust
so you can
predict something
in a system
when you have the complete data of the
system
when it comes to things that are
happening below the surface of the earth
we don't know what's happening we don't
have
sensors there we don't have instruments
down deep under the earth's surface
much of what's happening below the
surface is unknown to us we don't have
the data and when you don't have
sufficient data you can't make any
predictions
so that is why it is almost impossible
to predict earthquakes
because we don't have data of what's
happening below the surface of the earth
the
the subterranean world is almost unknown
to us we don't know almost we know next
to nothing
about what lies below the surface of the
earth we have some understanding of how
thick the earth's crust is how thick the
mantle is how thick is the magma layer
what the connect convection zone the
core of the earth we have some idea of
this but it's a very rudimentary idea we
we really haven't gone there and seen
how it is
so because we have so such an
insufficient data that's why we are not
able to predict earthquakes
current says can i understand advanced
mathematics like calculus tensors
ordinary differential equations partial
differential equations etc just through
self-study of course you can
whatever i have learned is entirely
through self-study i have never learned
a single thing
in school college or university in class
no teacher has ever taught me anything
whatever i have learned in my life is
only through 100
self-study whether it comes to
mathematics whether it comes to physics
science history geopolitics anything
i am entirely self-taught if i can do it
so can you
right so you can study mathematics from
from the very beginning um to the up to
the as advanced as you want to get
entirely through self-study
mathematics let's see learning
mathematics is very simple it's all
about solving problems the more problems
you solve the more you understand the
patterns of mathematics the hidden
patterns right and the laws and all that
so you can do it very easily on your own
self-study you can learn anything
tensors tensor
algebra tensor calculus
differential equations matrices whatever
whatever you want it's all possible
unvei says what is more mathematical
economics or physics both use a lot of
math but some of the topics are common
while some are exclusive to the
respective sciences i think economics is
not as mathematical as physics
physics i mean
all the mathematics that you can imagine
is used in physics but not but only some
of it is used in economics i think you
need calculus and differential equations
you need some matrices and some
linear algebra etc in
in economics but not much beyond that
but when it comes to physics we
essentially use all
of
mathematics in physics
so it is certainly physics that is more
mathematical than economics
bharat says i am from india south
had you read anybody anything about
freedom fighters from india south
between 1900 to 1950 in your schools do
india do in do northern india schools
teach anything about south india's
freedom fighters kings anything good in
general
in school we only read about bhagat
singh gandhi nehru bows etc we respect
them all but curious to know whether
north really knows about the south i
think
the south has been greatly neglected in
india's
textbooks
that is undeniable
we know very little about the south of
india very little is taught in school
about
uh southern india as compared to
northern india until 2016 2017 nobody
had heard of the chola dynasty
it is because of social media that today
people know about the cholas
because of people posting about the
chola empire on social media on twitter
facebook etc that's why people know
today about the cholas
our history textbooks did not teach
anything about the tulas or about the
cheras the pandyas and various other
other things from southern india right
so there has certainly been
a significant neglect of southern india
in the education system
the education system has always been
delhi centric north india centric
and this
disparated this neglect of the south
which is not as bad as the neglect of
the east in the northeast but it is
there and this has been used by the
dravidian parties to to to claim that uh
the south is marginalized and this is
because of the
aryan
dravidian divide and all that
so it is these
very poor policies of
the previous governments in india
that have led to this uh that have given
the chance to the political parties in
southern india the dravidian parties to
create this sense of alienation
it is very unfortunate
a great deal of harm has been done to
the
integrity and unity of the country by
these policies of the neruvian naruvian
regime
and post-naruvian regimes very
unfortunate so i agree that that there
is very little
that is taught in school
in history
about the kings and the empires and
kingdoms
and freedom fighters and culture
etc
of
the southern parts of india
sandeep says what is the connection
between jewish characters of abraham and
sarah
and the hindu gods brahma and saraswati
there is no connection none that i know
of
that's it
the the
jewish tradition the abrahamic tradition
is very different
from
the indian tradition
uh as far as from from the best that i
know
there is absolutely no connection
between
these jewish characters and the hindu
gods
none that i that i know of
tanoshi says can israel join the artemis
accord as india is one of the main
allies russia's took themselves out of
the rtms accord and planned to start
their own
lunar program with china
india can certainly join the program i
even heard in the news some time ago
that there is some discussion about
india participating in this the thing is
that this is a u.s led initiative
and the u.s will never leave
will never allow some other country to
take the lead in this
it will always be us first everybody
else later so if india wants to be a
major player
in geopolitics in space and become a
major civilization again
then india should do it on its own
india has the ability
to create a lunar program and space
program of its own a world-class program
we have all the wrong raw ingredients we
have all the
we have everything in place to do it
it's just about the political will
so i think it will be best for india to
participate to some extent but have our
own separate program to reach the moon
and go beyond
shankarjit says does the current indian
government care too much about elections
than doing the right thing why did they
revert the three farm laws to appease
some protesting farmers when it
benefited many of the farmers
do you support this move see we don't
have sufficient data or information to
say why they did this and i don't think
it's a political move to win elections
in punjab or to appease some farmers
there is something much bigger than this
going on i think it's a national
security issue which is why they've done
this
so i think i don't have enough
information to
to know
why this has been done but i would say
that we should
support the government
mr modi knows what he is doing
i mean if you look at his past track
record
he has usually made good decisions so i
think we should
support him
and
give him the time until 2024 to achieve
whatever he is trying to achieve
now
does the current indian government care
too much about elections you have to
care about elections in a democratic
electoral system you lose an election
you go out of power
would you like this government to go off
power and would like
a neruvian kind of regime to come back
in power in india would you is that what
you would like
the government has
to prioritize elections
that is the system we live in if they
don't care about elections somebody else
will come to power
and then what happens to all the plans
they have for the future of the country
it's going to go backwards
so the government has to care about
elections they have no option they have
no alternative there is the nature of
the system you are in it is an electoral
system
without elections you're done you're
finished
so it has to care about elections and i
don't think people should be upset about
that
okay we should always have one question
about aliens
so how would we react to finding aliens
can alien civilizations become a threat
to humanity let's say you are walking
on a dark road in the middle of the
night
and some unknown person comes towards
you
how would you react to that
you would react with extreme caution
right because you don't know whether
this person
is good or bad whether this person
represents a threat or not
similarly if we were to find intelligent
aliens we would have to react with
extreme caution we have to assume the
worst we have to assume that they are
threat they are a threat to humanity and
we will have
to take all necessary precautions
in that case
so the reaction to finding aliens will
be a reaction of extreme caution
and it can certainly cause
a
major threat to humanity
all right my friends that brings us to
an end of all these questions
it's almost two hours let me take a
couple of live chat questions
if i can
can i do i have any interesting
questions
live questions going on right now
garwal farmers ah this is interesting
her says the farmers are still going to
march onto the parliament and the
protests will still continue
on other issues
what should the government do in such a
case should repeal of laws be revoked
i think one of the good effects
of the repeal of these laws is that it
is going to show that the these
so-called farmers who are protesting
have some other agenda
the agenda was not the repeal of the
farm laws
even though the farm laws have now been
repealed they are still protesting
until now they are claiming they are
protesting because the farm laws are bad
so what are they protesting about now
it is very clear now that the agenda is
to destabilize the country
so i think it is good that they are
doing this it should now be highlighted
that the agenda was not simply the
repeal of the farm laws it is something
else
i don't think the government will repeal
the formula will repeal
or revoke the repeal of the farm laws
but
some action will have to be taken if
this goes out of hand
so this is a good question
one china policy i've already spoken
about
long-term allies
long term allah us or russia long term
allies india we have to go alone allies
will always keep changing
there are only temporary alliances and
temporary adversarial relationships
there is no long term alliance
russia is not powerful enough to be a
viable ally
the us i don't know how much we can
trust the u.s because they only i mean
they should care about their own
national interest
right now uh the common enemy is china
so we can have a temporary alliance with
the us but the u.s will never tolerate
a real rise of india as a potential
superpower so
we will have to keep that in mind
is there any other question
okay let me see
was akbar secular no thank you he was
not
no here what is secularism secularism is
the separation of church and state it
doesn't apply in the indian context so
no akbar was not secular by any means
joseph says what is dharma dharma is the
indian um
is the indian
tradition essentially the the different
schools of thought of india of india's
socio-cultural
and spiritual traditions
you have a num i think nine schools of
thought charvaka mansa both
of
vedanta sankhya yoga and so on so for
nine of these schools of thought and
there are many other schools of thought
too so all of these taken together these
these represent different world views
different philosophical and spiritual
world views
some of them
accept the
existence of some kind of god some of
them are explicitly polytheistic some of
them reject the existence of god
most of them believe in the law of karma
and so on and so forth so
the sum total of all of this it's a very
diverse
array of of world views but the sum
thought sum total all of of all this is
dharma
and
you
to simplify matters what is prescribed
in the vedas is dharma
but again some of these schools of
thought like jaina and buddha
jaina essentially they reject the
authority of the vedas so does
and
in terms of the both the dharma people
some people say it rejects the vedas
some people say it does not
if you if you read the
death bed discourse of gotham buddha he
essentially says that the vedas are
correct
so it's a matter of
conjecture some controversy but all of
this taken together is dharma
so that's a very simplistic and brief
answer to this question
all right my friends i'm gonna conclude
here
thank you very much for all your
questions i got more than 650 questions
this time so many great questions very
interesting questions i could only pick
up a few
so keep it coming guys and girls thank
you so much for all of your
participation your viewership your
support
thank you so much i'm very grateful and
i will see you same time same channel
tomorrow night until then take care
bye